# Valeria Pineda Romero

DATA SCIENTIST

MEXICO CITY, MX.

🛮 +52 444-548-1163 | 🔤 vv.pinedaromero@gmail.com | 😭 vpinedaromero.com | 🖸 github.com/ValeriaPineda23 | 🛅 linkedin.com/in/valeria-pineda-romero

### **Personal Profile**

A data scientist with team-oriented mentality and 3 years of hands-on experience implementing **machine learning models** for projects in education, warehouse operations, retail and business research. Knowledgeable about **data science**, **optimization problems**, **operations research**, and **report writing**. Primarily, looking for **Data Scientist** roles.

## Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Resideo San Luis Potosí, Mexico

Data Scientist April 2024 - Present

- Developed a predictive model with 85.3% accuracy to estimate delivery dates for non-stocked purchase orders in the United States and Canada. Collaborated with Data Engineering and E-commerce teams to deploy the solution and designed a shadow test framework to monitor and evaluate the model's performance in production.
- Led a cross-functional team of four data scientists and software engineers to develop an algorithm for identifying highly similar items, enabling the Product Information Management (PIM) team to review and confirm item variants displayed on the website. Oversaw application and database development to facilitate decision tracking.
- Created an algorithm to identify and link duplicate customer profiles during Snap One's acquisition by Resideo, enhancing data consistency and reducing database redundancy.
- Successfully transferred the Customer Churn Prediction Model from MSSQL to Snowflake, ensuring seamless integration with the new ERP system and uninterrupted delivery of churn predictions to the sales team, preserving operational efficiency and decision-making support.
- Technical Skills: Snowflake, SQL, Python with Jupyter Notebooks, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Scikit-learn, SSRS

**Resideo**San Luis Potosí, Mexico

BI Analyst Dec 2022 - April 2024

- Developed a Customer Churn Prediction Model with 95.8% recall, enabling targeted retention strategies that significantly reduced customer churn and improved business performance.
- Guided the Data Science Team in delivering three key projects: Sales Forecasting using Macroeconomic Indicators, Item Variants Detection Algorithm, and Customer Label Assignment Model.
- · Created, modified and optimized more than 50 sales and inventory reports using Microsoft SQL Server and SSRS Report Builder.
- Leveraged Snowflake to develop BI reports and deploy machine learning models.
- Technical Skills: Python (Jupyter Notebooks, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Scikit-learn), SQL, JavaScript, HTML, WebFocus, SSRS.

#### Education

#### Tecnológico de Monterrey

Monterrey, Mexico

MSc in Engineering - GPA: 4.0/4.0

Aug 2020 - Jun 2022

Courses: Data Science, Multiple Linear Regression, Machine Learning, Intelligent Systems, Data Analytics, Computing Fundamentals.

# Tecnologico de Monterrey

San Luis Potosi, Mexico

**B.S. in Industrial and Systems Engineering** - GPA: 3.7/4.0

Aug 2016 - Jun 2020

Courses: Statistics I, Statistics II, Optimization Models, Design and Analysis of Experiments, Statistics Engineering, Decision-Making Models

# **Relevant Projects**

#### Factors to improve online education, a study on the impact of COVID-19 on Delhi students

Monterrey, Mexico

Tecnológico de Monterrey

Feb 2022 - Jan 2023

- Developed a machine learning model (ROC AUC: 0.837) to identify demographic and behavioral factors affecting New Delhi students' online education during COVID-19.
- Research Publication: V. V. Pineda-Romero, C. E. Orozco-Mora and H. G. Ceballos, "Factors to improve online education: A study on the impact of COVID-19 on Delhi students," 2023 Future of Educational Innovation-Workshop Series Data in Action, Monterrey, Mexico, 2023, pp. 1-8, doi: 10.1109/IEEECONF56852.2023.10104773.
- Technical Skills: Python with Jupyter Notebooks, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Statsmodels, Pandas, Scikit-learn, XGBoost, LaTeX, SHAP.

#### A data mining-driven storage policy to improve order-picking efficiency

Queretaro, Mexico

Tecnológico de Monterrey

Nov 2021 - Jun 2022

- Designed class-based storage strategies using clustering techniques, reducing order-picking travel distance by 11.33% for a Mexican retail company.
- Technical Skills: Microsoft SQL Server, Python with Jupyter Notebooks, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, SciPy, Statsmodels, Pandas, Scikit-learn, LaTeX

# **Solution for the Precedence-Constrained Picker Routing Problem using Genetic Algorithms**

Monterrey, Mexico

Tecnológico de Monterrey

Sept 2020 - Jun 2022

- Applied Genetic Algorithms to optimize order-picking sequences, improving process efficiency by 30.2% for a Mexican retail company..
- Technical Skills: Microsoft SQL Server, Python with Jupyter Notebooks, Gurobi Python, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, LaTeX.